Samuel George Morton Papers 1819-1850 Mss.B.M843
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 2.25 Linear feet 5 boxes, 486 items.
  - Letter to Sam[uel] George Morton, August 4, [1839?]; 5" x 8"; Townsend, John Kirk, 1809-1851
    Cape May, N.J., A.L.S. 2p. and add. Requesting permission for Chevalier to use Academy's ornithological specimens.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 12, 1839; 8 1/2" x 11"; Powell, W. Byrd (William Byrd), 1799-1866
    Gainesville, Ala., A(?) L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning crania. Freeman Guide 425, also 2378.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 13, 1839; 8" x 10"; Powell, W. Byrd (William Byrd), 1799-1866
    Gainesville, Ala., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Requests copy of his book for G. Amison Osge (?)
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 23, 1839; 7 1/4" x 9"; Prichard, James Cowles, 1786-1848
    Bristol [Eng.], A.L.S. 3p. and add. Regarding his election to Academy. Concerning crania. Freeman Guide 1513.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 29, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Sullivant, Joseph, 1809-1882
    Columbus, O., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning his collection of Native American crania, ornaments, and "idols." Refers to Mr. Waggoner and Mr. Green. Freeman Guide 1306.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Sept. 9, 1839; 7 3/4" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning "The Quadrupeds of North America," and "Birds of America." Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Sept. 11, 1839; 7 3/4" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning British copyright of Morton's work.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Sept. 15, 1839; 7" x 8 1/2"; Randall, J. W.
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. "by politeness of the Mr. Nuttall." Concerning the work of Don B. de Cardenus.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 22, 1839; 8" x 10"; Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860
    [London?] A.L.S. 2p. and add. Sending an order for money to collect at "good" banks.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 29, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Buchanan, Joseph R. (Joseph Rodes), 1814-1899
    Bayou Teche, La., [c.]. A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Morton's work on crania. Offers his collection for study. Freeman Guide 1496.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 8, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Say, Lucy Way Sistaire, 1801-1886
    Cincinnati, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sending specimens of Anculotus.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 23, 1839; 7 3/4" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning his journey after he left Philadelphia. Mentions his "Birds."
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 30, 1839; 7 3/4" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 7, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Crania Americana.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 10, 1839; 8" x 10"; Ruschenberger, W. S. W., (William Samuel Waithman), 1807-1895
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning dedication of the "Crania Americana."
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 11, 1839; 7" x 9"; Hodgkin, Thomas, 1798-1866
    London, A.L.S. 2p. add. (Contains also a 2p. printed letter from J. Prichard to Dr. Hodgkin, May 20, 1839.) Introduces Dr. Lang. Concerning American crania.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 23, 1839; 8" x 10"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Boston, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Crania Americana. Calculates price of book in Britain. Mentions George Bancroft. Freeman Guide 1499.
  - Letter to Mr. Fuller(?), [c. 1839]; 7 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Caldwell, Charles, 1772-1853
    [c. 1839] A.L.S. 1p. and end. Encloses his opinion of the merits of [S.G. Morton's] Crania Americana.
  - Letter to Sam[uel] G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 13, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Albany, N.Y., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Morton's book and his collection of crania. Phrenology. Freeman Guide 1500.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Jan.(?) 27, 1840; 5" x 7 3/4"; Loyd, Mary Ann
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning her gift of a copy of F. A. Kempa (?). Religious matters.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 7, 1840; 7 3/4" x 6"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Albany, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Orders of Morton's book. Refers to Dr. Boardman and Mr. Watson.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 10, 1840; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, O., A.L.S.2p. and add. Sending shells for the cabinets of Morton's little sons. Refers to animal bones. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], Feb. 17, 1840; 7 1/4" x 9 1/4"; Prichard, James Cowles, 1786-1848
    Bristol [Eng.], A.L.S. 4p. Concerning the sale of his work. Freeman Guide 1514.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], Feb. 19, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New Haven, A.L.S. 2p. (On same sheet with letter from B. Silliman, Feb. 19,1840). Dr. Coates will write a better review of his book. Freeman Guide 1516
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 19, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (Contains also a letter from Geo. Combe to Dr. Morton, Feb. 19, 1840) Concerning Morton's book. Combe will write a review. Freeman Guide 1516.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 26, 1840; 8" x 10 1/4"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sending a check for deposit. Refers to his "small work on the Birds of our Country."
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 28, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New Haven, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Sends money for Morton's book. Refers to skulls, including Peruvian heads. Freeman Guide 3160.
  - Letter to Samuel Geo[rge] Morton, March 6, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New Haven, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning his editorial note on Morton's book. Freeman Guide 3161.
  - Letter to J[oseph] N[icholas] Nicollet, Washington, March 8, 1840; 9-3/4x8; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see S.G.Morton papers.) Formerly B M843.2. Received skulls of Indian tribes west of the Mississippi and thanks for his sending them.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 12, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; American Statistical Association
    Boston, Printed form S: Joseph B. Felt, recording secretary.. 1P, and add. Notification of election to honorary membership..
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, March 13, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New Haven, A.L.S. 4p. add. Concerning a notice in Silliman's Journal. Refers to Peruvian skulls. Freeman Guide 3162.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 27, 1840; 7" x 9"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Combe's review.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 1, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning Morton's book.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 24, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Thanks for your book.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 6, 1840; 7" x 9"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven A.L.S. 4p. add. Concerning a translation from the work of Humboldt.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 13, 1840; 7 1/4" x 9"; Van Rensselaer, Jeremiah
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning his intention to resign from profession for a while and sail to Europe.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l Geo[rge] Morton, May 21-24, 1840; 8 1/2" x 10 1/2" and 7 3/4" x 12 1/2"; Gliddon, George R. (George Robins), 1809-1857
    Alexandria, A.L.S. 3p. and enc. of 10p. and enc. Concerning his plan to return to America. Discusses skulls. Incudes various bils for collecting specimens.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 31, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New York, A.L.S, 1p. and add. Concerning the publication of his book in London. Refers to skulls.
  - Letter to Sam[uel] Geo[rge] Morton, June 24, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    London, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning sales of Morton's book in England. Advises increased publicity.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 6, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L. 1p. and add. (Signature has been cut off) Concerning payment due from Academy for Birds of America.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, July 18, 1840; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Slateford, near Edinburgh, A.L.S. 4p. add. Concerning a description of Morton's book. Refers to Jameson, other enemies of phrenology. Freeman Guide 1501.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 27, 1840; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Cisneros, José Rodriques
    Habana, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In Spanish.
  - Letter to S[amuel] George Morton, Aug. 7, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    U.S.S.Vincennes, Feejee Islands, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning his travels, including places and people he observed.
  - Letter to S[amuel] George Morton, Aug. 8, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    Feejee Islands, A.L.S. 8p. add. Concerning observation that species are "always adapted by Nature." Discusses examples.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], Aug. 15, 1840; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Macartney (?), John P.
    Mexico, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 2214.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 20, 1840; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Slateford, Edinburgh, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Morton's inheritance. Refers to Forbes' review of Morton's book. Freeman Guide 3163.
  - Letter to S[amuel George] Morton, Aug. 22, 1840; 8" x 10 1/4"; Engelmann, George, 1809-1884
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning skulls from Germany. Mentions a German work on fossils. Refers to Dr. Hirschfeld.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 27, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Griffin, Francis
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning skulls.
  - Letter to Samuel [George] Morton, Sept. 19, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Dorfeuille, Jennette
    Brooklyn, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Printed: E.R. Kellogg, Joseph Dorfeuille and the western museum - Journal of the Cincinnati society of natural history, v.22,no.4,1945.
    not located 4/2010
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Sept. 23, 1840; 7 3/4" x 10"; Gross, Jos[eph?] B.
    Saillerville, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning skulls, geography and geological matters. Mentions Dr. Coates.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l George Morton, Sept. 24, 1840; 8" x 10"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    On board Barque Eugenia off Sandy Hook, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning his voyage. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 3, 1840; 8" x 9"; Abert, John James, 1788-1863
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Requesting information about American natural scientists.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 6, 1840; 8x10; Clapp, A. (Asahel)
    New Albany, A.L.S. 2p. Requesting publications. Concerning geological fossils.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 12, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (Contains also a note by V.G. Audubon) Mentions his son Victor and his wife. Refers to Morton's book on diseases of the lung. Victor seeks Morton's advice.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 17, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Massachusetts Medical Society
    Boston, Printed form S: S.D. Townsend, corresponding secretary. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Nov. 6, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Powell, W. Byrd (William Byrd), 1799-1866
    Memphis, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning manuscript he sent to Am. Phrenological Journal. Mentions Prenol. Society in Mississippi.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Nov. 14, 1840; 6 3/4" x 8 3/4"; Stow, B.
    Sierra Leone, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (Contains also an autograph note by Dr. Morton.) Concerning shells, botany.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 30, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Markoe, Francis, 1801-1871
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Friendly letter. Mentions Dr. Borrough, Mr. Conrad, Mr. Audubon.
  - Letter to Samu[el]l G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 4, 1840; 7-3/4x9-1/2; Clapp, A. (Asahel)
    New Albany, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Ordering books.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l George Morton, Dec. 10, 1840; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    On board steamer, Great Western (?), A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning fossil he forgot to take.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Nov. 4, 1840(?); 8 1/2" x 10 1/2"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Slateford near Edinburgh, A.L.S. 1p. (On reverse of this sheet is a printed prospectus of S.G. Morton's Crania Americana, and a listing of works by George Combe) Concerning his book on crania. Refers to Phrenological Meeting. Freeman Guide 1502.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l George Morton, Jan. 3, 1841; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    London, A.L.S. 4p. add.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 26, 1841; 8" x 10"; Hitchcock, Edward, 1793-1864
    Amherst, L.S. 1p. and add. Invitation to attend meeting of Assoc. of American Geologists.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 3, 1841; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Lederer, L.
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (On same sheet with letter from Lederer to J. S. Phillips, Feb. 3, 1841) Concerning scientists in Vienna.
  - Letter to J.S. Phillips, Feb. 3, 1841; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Lederer, L.
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (On same sheet with letter to S.G. Morton, Feb. 3, 1841.) Concerning scientists in Vienna.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 14, 1841; 8 1/2" x 10 1/2"; Engelmann, George, 1809-1884
    St. Louis, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning skulls from Germany. Mentions Dr. King. Geology.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 17, 1841; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Maclure, Alexander
    (?), New Harmony, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Gives biographical date about his brother, William Maclure. Printed: APS Proceedings, v.91,no.3,1947, page 248. Refers to Academy, Dr. Bidges, David Dale Owen, Mr. Burrough, and Mrs. Say.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], March 30, 1841; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Macartney (?), John P.
    Mexico, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning skulls. Refers to Mr. Cortina. Freeman Guide 2214.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, April 9, 1841; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Mercantile Library of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, L.S.: Thos. P. Cope, Isaac Barton, Charles S. Woods, Wm. L. Schaffer, H.C. Corbit, Joseph C. Grubb, Jno. Fausset(?), Committee. 2p. and add. Ask whether Morton would deliver lectures.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, April 20, 1841; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Bird, Robert Montgomery, 1806-1854
    New Castle, Del., A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his election to chair of Materia Medica at Univ. of Penn.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 27, 1841; 6 1/4" x 7 1/2"; Locke, John, 1792-1856
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Samuel] G[eorge] Morton, April 28, 1841; 7 3/4" x 10"; Franklin Institute (Philadelphia, Pa.)
    Philadelphia, A.L.S: Jas. C. Booth, chairman, Com. manufactures. 1p. Thanks for donation of earthen vessel and contents.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, April 29, 1841; 7-3/4x9-3/4; Clapp, A. (Asahel)
    New Albany, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning fossils.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], May 20, 1841; 8" x 10"; Nicollet, J.N. (Joseph Nicolas), 1786-1843
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p. Refers to Mr. Conrad's trip to the Chesapeake. Sends publications. FILM403 FRAME 5-5
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, June 1, 1841; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Boston Society of Natural History
    Boston, L.S: Augustus A. Gould, Ch. K. Dillaway, W.I. Bowditch, Committee. 1p. Invitation to present address at the annual meeting.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 2, 1841; 7 3/4" x 10"; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, L.S: Walter R. Johnson, John P. Wetherill, Robert Bridges, Committee. 2p. and add. Thanks for commemoration of their late president (Maclure).
  - Letter to J[oseph] N[icholas] Nichollet, March 8, 1842; 10x8; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Morton papers.) B M843.1. Returns fossils and will return publication, after he translates a few more passages. Freeman Guide 2995.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], May 17, 1845; 4 1/2" x 7 1/4"; Morton, James
    Little Island, A.L.S. 8p. Friendly letter from cousin. Family matters.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 11, 1845; 7 1/2" x 9"; Fitzgerald, G.
    Dungarvan, A.L.S. 4p. Friendly letter. Family matters.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, July 1, 1845; 7 1/2" x 9"; Doyle, Charles
    Clonmel, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Former servant of Morton's cousin James asking for support.
  - Letter [Samuel George Morton], Aug. 24, 1845; 4 1/2" x 7 1/2"; Morton, James
    Little Island, A.L.S. 4p. Friendly letter from cousin.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], Sept. 16, 1845; 4 1/2" x 7 1/4"; Morton, James
    Little Island, A.L. 4p. (Signature cut off) Thanks for money for servant Charles Doyle.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 25, 1846; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    Introduces Ed. de Verneuil from France.
    Formerly B M843.3.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G. Morton, July 10, 1847; 7 3/4" x 10"; Pease, W. H.
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Fossils for the Academy [of natural sciences of Philadelphia]. Deposited by the Academy of natural sciences of Philadelphia.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, May 23, 1848; 4 1/4" x 7"; Marshall, B. A.
    Liverpool, A.L.S. 2p. Recommends servant John Furlong.
  - To Dr. Grant, October 23, 1848; ALS, 2p; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    1986-1114ms
    Returns books. Refers to donation of rattlesnake to Academy.
    Formerly B M843.4.
  - Some remarks on the infrequence of mixed offspring between the European and Australian races., April, 1850; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    A.Dr. of D. 4 leaves. Deposited by the Academy of Natural Sciences, May 1943. Includes numbers of natives and half-breeds in Australian settlements.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], June 25, 1850; 7 1/4" x 9"; Morton, James
    Little Island, A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter from cousin. Refers to the death of Morton's son George.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], Dec. 28, 1850; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Zantzinger, William S.
    A.L.S. 1p. Mr. Weber will take Morton's portrait.
  - Letter to Edw. J. Nolan, May 2, 1911; 8" x 10 1/2"; Hrdlička, Aleš, 1869-1943
    Washington, T.L.S. 1p. Deposited by the Academy of natural sciences, May 1943. Concerning significance of Morton's anthropological work. Freeman Guide 1510.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 2-5, undated; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Conrad, T. A.
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning geological fossils. Refers to difficulties in locating fossils, finding assistants.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, undated; 7 3/4" x 10"; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831
    n.d. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sending Hooker's Exotic Flora.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], undated; 7" x 9"; Franks, Frederick
    n.d. A.L.S. 2p. and end. Thanks for minerals.
  - [Note relative to aborigines of Peru], undated; 7 1/4" x 9"; Pentland, Joseph Barclay, 1797-1873
    D. 2p. Concerning skulls. Freeman Guide 3167.
  - Letter to Miss Senior (?)., undated; 4 1/2" x 7 1/2"; Sankey (?), M. E.
    A.L.S. 4p. add.
  - Newspaper clippings re. Dr. Morton's death, undated; 6.0 Item(s)
    Unmarked folder with several items, including newspaper clippings (obit), envelope (1850), sketch for Morton’s “Tablet” (grave stone), three loose mss. pages (table of contents?).
- Series II. Journal, 1833 - ca. 1837; Mss.B.M843d; 1 vol.
  Record of a trip taken by Morton to the West Indies, including observations on life, work, agriculture, and slavery on Barbados and other islands.
  - Diary of Trip to the West Indies, and notebook, 1833-1837; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    Scope and Content note
    Diary and notebook.
- Series III. Craniological Sketches, ca. 1838; Mss.B.M843s; 11 items
  Native American Images note: Original watercolor and ink sketches of skulls from such tribes as the Algonquin, Cayuga, Cherokee, Osage, and Seminoles. Published in Morton’s work Crania Americana (1839), the artists include James Tooley, F. Davis, H. Heinemann, and W. Eberlein. The burial mound locations are primarily in the Northeast and Mid-Western United States, but include a Peruvian Aymara tomb.
  - Skull, frontal view, Unidentified artist
  - Skull, lateral view
    Unidentified artist
  - Frontal view of skull "from a mound at the corner of Main & 3rd Streets, Cinti., Ohio", Davis, F.
  - Lateral view of skull "from a mound at the corner of Main and 3rd Sts., Cincinnati, Ohio", ca. 1838; Right side view of skull.; Davis, F.
    Inscription: "From a mound at the corner of Main and 3rd Streets, Cin, Ohio. F. Davis Del."
  - "Original drawing of a Botocudo cranium in the cabinet of Dr. Blumenbach.", Eberlein, W.
    "Sent me by the Prince Maxn. De Wied, and published in the Crania Americana."
  - "From a mound at the Junction of Broad & Holston Rivers, Kentucky.", Heinemann
    "The Skull is in my collection & is figured ion the Crania Americana. From G. Troost."
  - "From and Indian cemetery near Nashville, Tennessee.", Heinemann
    "Sent me by Prof. Troost."
  - "From a mound near Natchez, Mississippi.", Tooley, James
    "This cranium is now in my collection. From Mr. James Tooley, Jr." On verso: "The skull, of which this drawing correc tly represent, was taken from an ancient mound in Jefferson County, near Silver town, Mississippi, in 1838 by James Tooley, Junior."
  - "A tomb of the ancient Aymara, Peruvians, on an island in the Lake Titicaca -- copied from a plate in d'Orbigny's `L'homme Americain.' ", Unidentified artist
    Partial pencil sketch of cow of verso.
  - "Skeleton exhumed at Fall-River, in Rhode Island, A.D.", Unidentified artist
    Stipple drawing of burial and lateral view of skull.
  - "Skeletons of Naumkeag Indians, as exposed in excavations at Salem, Mass.", Unidentified artist
    Stipple drawing of four skeletons.
  - Sketches of human skeletons, undated; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851
    sketches
- Series IV. Samuel George Morton Microfilm (Film 1413), 1838-1844
  Approximately 220 items forming part of a bound volume of incoming correspondence, a companion to the materials in Series I. Letters relate to American Indians, archaeology, Egyptology, and phrenology. Originals property of Dr. Hugh Montgomery, March 1980. The letters are to Morton unless otherwise stated.
  - From Charles Pickering, 1843 Dec. 17; 1
  - From T. Wm. Harris, 185_ April 5; 1a
  - From T. Wn. Harris to Publishing Comm. of Journal of Acad. of Nat. Sciences, n.d.; 2
  - From H. Piddington, 1838 June 6; 3
  - Certificate of membership in British & Foreign Aborigines Protection Society, 1839 Jan. 23; 4
  - From George Combe, 1839 March 6; 5
  - From Samuel Forry, 1839 June 27; 6
  - From G[erard] Troost, 1838 Oct. 31; 7
  - From James W. Clements, 1839 May 7; 8
  - From James W. Clements, 1839 July 5; 8a
  - From T. Gomez de la Cortina, 1840 [UNK]. 28; 9
  - From Edward Hirschfeld, 1840 May 28; 10
  - From Committee of Pathological Soc. of Phila., 1839 Oct. 1; 11
  - From Lucy W. Say, 1840 May 23; 12
  - From Committee to establish Hospitals in China [N.Chapman, Robly Dunglison, Geo. B. Wood, S.G.Morton, J.K.Mitchell], 1841 Jan. 6; 13
  - From George Morris, 1840 Aug. 5; 14
  - Broadside. Proceedings of the Phrenological Assoc. Held at Glasgow, 1840 Sept.; 15
  - From J.C. Prichard, 1839 Oct. 3; 16
  - From Jos. U. Swift, 1840 Dec. 7; 17
  - From J.C. Prichard, 1841 March 24; 18
  - From Thomas S. Page, 1841 April 5; 19
  - From Joseph B. Gross, 1841 Nov. 1; 20